"Do Vitamin C Supplements
Help with Anxiety"
“Emerging evidence suggests that
higher daily intake of ﬁber-rich
fruits and vegetables is associated
with lower incidences of anxiety
in adults and at the same time,
greater happiness, higher life
satisfaction, and greater
emotional well-being.”
So, “persuading people to
consume more fruits and vegetables
may not only benefit their
physical health in the long-run,
but also their mental
well-being in the short-run.”
Fruit consumption, for example,
has protective association
with leading killers like
heart disease, stroke, diabetes,
and cancer, as well as
depression. The question is why?
Several different mechanisms
have been proposed.
For example, it may be the
antioxidants and anti-inflammatory
properties of produce, scavenging
the free radicals that are
involved in some of the
inflammation associated with depression.
If that’s the case, what about
just taking vitamin C supplements?
The brain has some of the highest
levels of vitamin C in the body;
so, the thought is if
we take extra vitamin C,
it may have some sort of
therapeutic role in brain diseases,
especially given that
it’s not just an antioxidant,
but also has other critical
functions in the brain such as
helping to build
neurotransmitters like dopamine.
But you don’t know
whether it actually helps,
until you... put it to the test.
One study found a beneficial
effect of adding vitamin C as an
adjunct treatment to an
antidepressant, while another study
found no benefit from
vitamin C supplementation.
So, there are mixed results
for vitamin C and depression.
Here’s another study that
found no benefit when it came to
depression, but those
randomized to vitamin C instead of
placebo pills did show a
significant decrease in anxiety level.
And this wasn’t only
seen in this study.
The effects of oral
vitamin C supplementation
on anxiety in students:
a double-blind, randomized,
placebo-controlled trial.
High school students were
given 500mg a day or placebo.
500mg of vitamin C is
about what you’d find
in five oranges, four
yellow kiwifruit or guavas,
or one and a half
yellow bell peppers.
Within just two weeks, the vitamin C
reduced anxiety compared to
placebo, along with providing
a significant drop in heart rate.
Given these data showing
vitamin C may have
anxiety-reducing effect,
researchers sought to find out
if only a single dose could
acutely affect emotional states.
And indeed, within only two
hours of taking some C,
subjects experienced a
significant drop in anxiety
compared to placebo,
though only among those
who started out the most
anxious in the first place.
As a bonus, vitamin C
supplementation may lower
your blood pressure a
few points, but whole fruits
and vegetables can do
the same thing and may even
do it better for those
who need it the most.
As I’ve shown previously,
even just adding two servings
of fruits and vegetables a
day can have psychological
well-being benefits
within only two weeks.
And you won’t be put at risk
of kidney stones like you would
with vitamin C supplements,
though that appears to be
only a problem in men.